Chris Marlow: So I'm glad
Jason has got some fans here.
I too met him
fairly recently in Oxford last year.
And just picking up from what Sophia
was saying earlier on about representation
matters, I think he is a perfect
example isn't he of
an emerging black
British scholar
that one hopes will be a role model
and a signal for change.
So he made history
earlier this year
when he was appointed as Professor
of Sociology of Education at Cambridge,
and he was filling some very big shoes
because the predecessor was Diane Reay,
who I'm sure
many of you know.
But I think what makes it
all the more remarkable in Jason's
case is his
history, his life history.
He was born in 1985,
so he's a relatively young professor.
He's I think the fourth or fifth
black professor at Cambridge,
but he's the youngest.
He was born in modest circumstances,
a council estate in Clapham.
And more significant, I think, is that
he was diagnosed as autistic
at three years old, at three years of age,
and also because of what I think
is termed global development delay.
didn't learn to speak
until he was 11
and then didn't
learn to write until he was 18.
And he had, beyond that
a meteoric rise through the academy.
He was,
I think, at Surrey
University, did a B.A. and an M.A.
in Education,
a PGCE, trained as a teacher,
as a PE teacher,
and then went on to an M.Ed and a PhD
at Liverpool John Moores University.
Apart from his appointment at Cambridge,
he's also a visiting professor
at Nelson Mandela University
in South Africa,
and his work principally sits
in, I suppose, what you might call
decolonizing the academy.
I'm just looking
at some of his interests here
and his key publication,
and the one that brought him to
my attention
was the 2018
book, Dismantling Race in Higher Education,
subtitled Racism, Whiteness
and Decolonizing the Academy.
And that was edited with Heidi Mirza.
And it's a fascinating, really varied
edited collection, very intersectional.
So it draws on black studies, disability,
race, social class, mobility.
And I think and I'm sure colleagues
will have mentioned this before,
there are, there are two or three,
I think, probably really salient
publications that that gave impetus
to this body of work and to the
decolonization within the Academy,
certainly within HE.
And I think I would argue
that this was certainly one of them.
A few key points from it.
He uses
the acronym BAME, and I know
that's not necessarily current these days,
but he says, for example, it's argued BAME
students are less likely to be admitted
to elite Russell Group universities
than white applicants with similar grades
you know and asked the question, why?
What's going on here?
What are the systemic barriers to that?
He talks very eloquently,
very persuasive, and very personally
about the mistreatment
within the academy of scholars of colour,
citing things like unfair workloads,
precarious contracts,
racial microaggressions.
And the sense
that that builds, that cumulatively that builds
to othering, that they are,
they define themselves as outsiders.
And it's that imposter syndrome.
More positively, I think he talks about,
and I quote, the irresistible rise
of decolonizing movements
to disrupt Western epistemologies.
I particularly want to flag this up because
this is where it's really,
really strong, where he and indeed
the other contributors are very, very keen
to deploy students
and include students as agents of change
and two particular initiatives,
two particular questions are raised.
Number one, why is my curriculum white?
That's the question
that students are encouraged to ask.
And the other one,
why isn't my professor black?
And I think those two questions
so salient,
so powerful, so potent.
And just one more little thing here.
And this isn't from Jason's work within the book,
this is actually Sara Ahmed in chapter 19,
and she talks about EDI
practices in academia
and she quotes,
sorry,
my quote is: tick box exercises, that's
how she describes them,
to create a happy impression,
but actually no long lasting changes
for BAME staff.
I hope, I mean that was written in 2018.
I hope that that's perhaps no longer the case
given the work that's going on
and I just thought I'd finish
with a great quotation from the book.
It's not actually from Jason,
it's from Audre Lorde, 2007
and it's this.
For the master's tools,
we will never dismantle
the master's house.
They may allow us to temporarily
beat him at his own games,
but they will never enable us
to bring about genuine change.
And I think what Jason
typifies, what he exemplifies
is that desire for change and is,
I think, probably a real beacon
of hope in and beyond the academy.
I think what he's giving us with his work
are the theoretical
and the conceptual tools
to challenge the status quo
and the fact that he is a first rate
scholar,
that he has social justice at his
at the heart of his work
is just brilliant.
And I would love if we could
get him to Lancaster
one way or another by hook or by crook.
I think it would be brilliant
to have him in the department perhaps
running a seminar or something similar,
but that's my quick take on Jason Arday.
I hope you've found it interesting.
Thank you very much.